is the community itself, is the audience. And you know from personal experience that when you go to the movies, you walk into a movie theater, and if it's empty, you're delighted, because nothing's going to be between you and the movie. You can spread out, put your legs over the top of the stadium seats, eat your popcorn and just enjoy it. But if you walk into a live theater and you see that the theater is half full, your heart sinks. You're disappointed immediately, because whether you knew it or not, you were coming to that theater to be part of an audience. You were coming to have the collective experience of laughing together, crying together, holding your breath together to see what's going to happen next. You may have walked into that theater as an individual consumer, but if the theater does its job, you've walked out with a sense of yourself as part of a whole, as part of a community. That's built into the DNA of my art form. Twenty-five hundred years later, Joe Papp decided that the culture should belong to everybody in the United States of America, and that it was his job to try to deliver on that promise. He created Free Shakespeare in the Park. And Free Shakespeare in the Park is based on a very simple idea, the idea that the best theater, the best art that we can produce, should go to everybody and belong to everybody, and to this day, every summer night in Central Park, 2,000 people are lining up to see the best theater we can provide for free. It's not a commercial transaction. In 1967, 13 years after he figured that out, he figured out something else, which is that the democratic circle was not complete by just giving the people the classics. We had to actually let the people create their own classics and take the stage. And so in 1967, Joe opened the Public Theater downtown on Astor Place, and the first show he ever produced was the world premiere of "Hair." That's the first thing he ever did that wasn't Shakespeare. Clive Barnes in The Times said that it was as if Mr. Papp took a broom and swept up all the refuse from the East Village streets onto the stage at the Public. (Laughter) He didn't mean it complimentarily, but Joe put it up in the lobby, he was so proud of it. (Laughter) (Applause) And what the Public Theater did over the next years with amazing shows like "For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide / When the Rainbow Is Enuf," "A Chorus Line," and -- here's the most extraordinary example I can think of: Larry Kramer's savage cry of rage about the AIDS crisis, "The Normal Heart." Because when Joe produced that play in 1985, there was more information about AIDS in Frank Rich's review in the New York Times than the New York Times had published in the previous four years. Larry was actually changing the dialogue about AIDS through writing this play, and Joe was by producing it. I was blessed to commission and work on Tony Kushner's "Angels in America," and when doing that play and along with "Normal Heart," we could see that the culture was actually shifting, and it wasn't caused by the theater, but the theater was doing its part to change what it meant to be gay in the United States. And I'm incredibly proud of that. (Applause) When I took over Joe's old job at the Public in 2005, I realized one of the problems we had was a victim of our own success, which is: Shakespeare in the Park had been founded as a program for access, and it was now the hardest ticket to get in New York City. People slept out for two nights to get those tickets. What was that doing? That was eliminating 98 percent of the population from even considering going to it. So we refounded the mobile unit and took Shakespeare to prisons, to homeless shelters, to community centers in all five boroughs and even in New Jersey and Westchester County. And that program proved something to us that we knew intuitively: people's need for theater is as powerful as their desire for food or for drink. It's been an extraordinary success, and we've continued it. And then there was yet another barrier that we realized we weren't crossing, which is a barrier of participation. And the idea, we said, is: How can we turn theater from being a commodity, an object, back into what it really is -- a set of relationships among people? And under the guidance of the amazing Lear deBessonet, we started the Public Works program, which now every summer produces these immense Shakespearean musical pageants, where Tony Award-winning actors and musicians are side by side with nannies and domestic workers and military veterans and recently incarcerated prisoners, amateurs and professionals, performing together on the same stage. And it's not just a great social program, it's the best art that we do. And the thesis of it is that artistry is not something that is the possession of a few. Artistry is inherent in being a human being. Some of us just get to spend a lot more of our lives practicing it. And then occasionally -- (Applause) you get a miracle like "Hamilton," Lin-Manuel's extraordinary retelling of the foundational story of this country through the eyes of the only Founding Father who was a bastard immigrant orphan from the West Indies. And what Lin was doing is exactly what Shakespeare was doing. He was taking the voice of the people, the language of the people, elevating it into verse, and by doing so, ennobling the language and ennobling the people who spoke the language. And by casting that show entirely with a cast of black and brown people, what Lin was saying to us, he was reviving in us our greatest aspirations for the United States, our better angels of America, our sense of what this country could be, the inclusion that was at the heart of the American Dream. And it unleashed a wave of patriotism in me and in our audience, the appetite for which is proving to be insatiable. But there was another side to that, and it's where I want to end, and it's the last story I want to talk about. Some of you may have heard that Vice President-elect Pence came to see "Hamilton" in New York. And when he came in, some of my fellow New Yorkers booed him. And beautifully, he said, "That's what freedom sounds like." And at the end of the show, we read what I feel was a very respectful statement from the stage, and Vice President-elect Pence listened to it, but it sparked a certain amount of outrage, a tweetstorm, and also an internet boycott of "Hamilton" from outraged people who had felt we had treated him with disrespect. I looked at that boycott and I said, we're getting something wrong here. All of these people who have signed this boycott petition, they were never going to see "Hamilton" anyway. It was never going to come to a city near them. If it could come, they couldn't afford a ticket, and if they could afford a ticket, they didn't have the connections to get that ticket. They weren't boycotting us; we had boycotted them. And if you look at the red and blue electoral map of the United States, and if I were to tell you, "Oh, the blue is what designates all of the major nonprofit cultural institutions," I'd be telling you the truth. You'd believe me. We in the culture have done exactly what the economy, what the educational system, what technology has done, which is turn our back on a large part of the country. So this idea of inclusion, it has to keep going. Next fall, we are sending out on tour a production of Lynn Nottage's brilliant, Pulitzer Prize-winning play "Sweat." Years of research in Redding, Pennsylvania led her to write this play about the deindustrialization of Pennsylvania: what happened when steel left, the rage that was unleashed, the tensions that were unleashed, the racism that was unleashed by the loss of jobs. We're taking that play and we're touring it to rural counties in Pennsylvania, Ohio, Michigan, Minnesota and Wisconsin. We're partnering with community organizations there to try and make sure not only that we reach the people that we're trying to reach, but that we find ways to listen to them back and say, "The culture is here for you, too." Because -- (Applause) we in the culture industry, we in the theater, have no right to say that we don't know what our job is. It's in the DNA of our art form. Our job "... is to hold up, as 'twere, a mirror to nature; to show scorn her image, to show virtue her appearance, and the very age its form and pressure." Our job is to try to hold up a vision to America that shows not only who all of us are individually, but that welds us back into the commonality that we need to be, the sense of unity, the sense of whole, the sense of who we are as a country. That's what the theater is supposed to do, and that's what we need to try to do as well as we can. Thank you very much. (Applause)
c'est la communauté, c'est le public. Vous savez d'expérience que lorsque vous allez voir un film, vous rentrez dans un cinéma et, s'il est vide, vous êtes ravi car il n'y aura rien entre vous et le film. Vous pouvez vous étaler, mettre vos jambes sur les sièges, manger votre pop-corn et en profiter. Mais si vous entrez dans un théâtre et que vous voyez que le théâtre est à moitié plein, votre cœur se serre. Vous êtes immédiatement déçu car, que vous le sachiez ou non, vous veniez dans ce théâtre pour faire partie d'un public. Vous veniez pour avoir une expérience collective, pour rire ensemble, pleurer ensemble, retenir votre souffle ensemble, voir ce qu'il se passe ensuite. Vous êtes peut-être entré dans ce théâtre en tant que consommateur individuel mais si le théâtre joue son rôle, vous en sortez avec un sentiment que vous faites partie d'un ensemble, partie d'une communauté. Cela est inscrit dans l'ADN de ma forme d'art. Vingt-cinq siècles plus tard, Joe Papp a décidé que la culture devrait appartenir à tout le monde aux États-Unis d'Amérique et que c'était son rôle d'essayer de tenir cette promesse. Il a créé Free Shakespeare in the Park. Free Shakespeare in the Park est fondé sur une idée très simple : le meilleur théâtre, le meilleur art que nous pouvons produire devrait être accessible par tous et appartenir à tous et, aujourd'hui encore, tous les soirs d'été à Central Park, 2 000 personnes sont dans les gradins pour voir le meilleur théâtre que nous pouvons offrir gratuitement. Ce n'est pas une transaction commerciale. En 1967, 13 ans après avoir compris cela, il a compris autre chose : le cercle démocratique n'était pas complet simplement en offrant les classiques aux gens. Nous devions laisser les gens créer leurs propres classiques et monter sur scène. En 1967, Joe a ouvert le Public Theater en ville, sur l'Astor Place, et la première pièce qu'il a produite fut la première mondiale de « Hair ». C'est la première chose qu'il a faite en dehors de Shakespeare. Clive Barnes dans The Times a dit que M. Papp avait pris un balai et balayé tous les déchets des rues d'East Village pour les amener sur scène au Public. (Rires) Ce n'était pas un compliment, mais Joe l'a accroché dans le hall d'entrée, il en était si fier. (Rires) (Applaudissements) Ce que le Public Theater a fait les années suivantes avec des pièces géniales telles que « For Colored Girls Who Have Considered Suicide / When the Rainbow Is Enuf », « Chorus Line » et -- l'exemple le plus extraordinaire qui me vient à l'esprit : le cri de rage sauvage de Larry Kramer au sujet de la crise du SIDA, « The Normal Heart ». Quand Joe a produit cette pièce en 1985, il y avait plus d'informations au sujet du SIDA dans la critique de Frank Rich dans le New York Times que ce qu'en avait publié le New York Times en quatre ans. Larry a changé le dialogue au sujet du SIDA en écrivant cette pièce et Joe l'a produite. J'ai eu la chance de diriger et travailler sur « Angels in America » de Tony Kushner et durant cette pièce, ainsi qu'avec « The Normal Heart », nous pouvions voir que la culture changeait et cela n'était pas dû au théâtre, mais le théâtre jouait son rôle pour changer ce que c'était d'être gay aux États-Unis. J'en suis incroyablement fier. (Applaudissements) Quand j'ai pris la relève de Joe au Public en 2005, j'ai réalisé qu'un des problèmes était d'être victime de notre succès : Shakespeare in the Park avait été fondé comme un programme d'accès et c'était maintenant le billet le plus difficile à obtenir de New York. Des gens dormaient dehors pendant deux nuits pour obtenir un billet. Qu'est-ce que je faisais ? Cela empêchait 98% de la population de ne serait-ce qu'envisager d'y aller. Nous avons recréé l'unité mobile et avons amené Shakespeare dans des prisons, des refuges, des centres communautaires dans les cinq quartiers, et dans le New Jersey, et dans le comté de Westchester. Ce programme nous a démontré une chose que nous savions intuitivement : le besoin de théâtre des gens est aussi fort que leur désir de nourriture ou d'un verre. Cela a été une réussite extraordinaire et nous avons continué. Il y a encore une autre barrière que nous avons franchie sans le savoir, la barrière de la participation. L'idée était : comment le théâtre pouvait-il passer d'une commodité, d'un objet, et redevenir ce qu'il est vraiment : un ensemble de relations entre des gens ? Sous la direction du génial Lear deBessonet, nous avons lancé le programme Public Works qui, chaque été, produit ces énormes spectacles musicaux shakespeariens où des acteurs et musiciens ayant remporté un Tony jouent aux côtés d'assistantes maternelles et d'employés de maison, de vétérans et de prisonniers récemment incarcérés, d'amateurs et de professionnels, tous ensemble sur la même scène. Ce n'est pas qu'un super programme social, c'est le meilleur art que nous faisons. La thèse à la base de cela est que le talent artistique n'est pas détenu seulement par quelques-uns. Le talent artistique est inhérent au fait d'être un être humain. Certains passent simplement plus de temps durant leur vie à l'exercer. Et occasionnellement -- (Applaudissements) il y a un miracle tel que « Hamilton », l'adaptation extraordinaire de l'histoire de la fondation de notre pays de Lin-Manuel à travers les yeux du seul Père fondateur qui était un orphelin immigrant et bâtard venant des Antilles. Ce que Lin a fait, c'est exactement ce que Shakespeare a fait. Il a pris la voix du peuple, la langue du peuple, l'a élevée en vers et, ce faisant, a ennobli la langue et a ennobli les gens parlant la langue. En ayant une distribution entièrement composée de personnes noires et de couleur, Lin nous a dit, a ravivé en nous nos plus grandes aspirations pour les États-Unis, le meilleur de la nature de l'Amérique, notre idée de ce que ce pays pourrait être, l'inclusion qui était au cœur du rêve américain. Cela a libéré une vague de patriotisme en moi et au sein du public, dont l'appétit se révèle insatiable. Il y a une autre facette avec laquelle je veux terminer, c'est la dernière histoire dont je veux parler. Certains ont peut-être entendu que le vice-président Pence est venu voir « Hamilton » à New York. Quand il est entré, certains de mes camarades new-yorkais l'ont hué. Admirablement, il a dit : « C'est le bruit de la liberté. » A la fin du spectacle, nous avons lu ce qui me semble être une déclaration très respectueuse et le vice-président Pence l'a écoutée mais cela a suscité une certaine indignation, un déferlement de tweets, et un boycott de « Hamilton » sur Internet de la part des gens ayant eu l'impression que nous lui avions manqué de respect. J'ai considéré ce boycott et j'ai dit que nous ne faisions pas ce qu'il fallait. Tous ces gens ayant signé la pétition de boycott n'auraient jamais vu « Hamilton » de toute façon. Le spectacle ne passera jamais près de chez eux. S'il passait, ils ne pourront pas payer le billet et s'ils ont l'argent pour le billet, ils n'ont pas les relations pour l'obtenir. Ils ne nous boycottaient pas, nous les avions boycottés. Si vous regardez la carte électorale bleue et rouge des États-Unis et si je vous disais que le bleu désignait les principales institutions culturelles à but non lucratif, je vous dirais la vérité. Vous me croiriez. Nous avons fait dans la culture exactement ce que l'économie, le système éducatif et la technologie ont fait : tourner le dos à une grande partie du pays. Cette idée d'inclusion doit persister. A l'automne prochain, nous envoyons en tournée une production de la géniale Lynn Nottage, une pièce ayant reçu un prix Pulitzer : « Sweat ». Des années de recherche à Redding, en Pennsylvanie, l'ont poussée à écrire cette pièce au sujet de la désindustrialisation de la Pennsylvanie : ce qu'il s'est passé à la disparition de l'acier, la rage provoquée, les tensions provoquées, le racisme provoqué par la perte d'emplois. Nous partons en tournée avec cette pièce dans les comtés ruraux de la Pennsylvanie, de l'Ohio, du Michigan, du Minnesota et du Wisconsin. Nous avons des partenariats avec des organisations communautaires afin de nous assurer de toucher les gens que nous voulons toucher, mais aussi de trouver des façons de les écouter en retour et de dire que la culture est également là pour eux. Parce que -- (Applaudissements) nous dans l'industrie de la culture, nous au théâtre, n'avons pas le droit de dire que nous ignorons quel est notre rôle. C'est dans l'ADN de notre forme d'art. Notre rôle est « d'être le miroir de la nature, de montrer à la vertu ses propres traits, à l'infamie sa propre image, et au temps même sa forme et ses traits ». Notre rôle est d'offrir à l'Amérique une image qui montre non seulement qui nous sommes tous individuellement, mais qui nous réunit au sein de cette communauté que nous devons être, la notion d'unité, la notion d'ensemble, la notion de notre identité en tant que pays. C'est cela que le théâtre est censé faire et que nous devons essayer de faire autant que possible. Merci beaucoup. (Applaudissements)